Guide to the Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn papers
1948-1985
YCAL MSS 177
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(5 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, writings and notes, photographs, and newspaper clippings relating to Sister Bernetta Quinn's scholarly work on the poetry of Ezra Pound and other modern poets. Correspondents include Robert Bly, Guy Davenport, Caroline Gordon, James Laughlin, Denise Levertov, Robert Lowell, Mary de Rachewiltz, Olga Rudge, Holly Stevens, Allen Tate, and Robert Penn Warren. Subjects include Sister Bernetta's scholarly work; writing and American poetry in general; conference and symposia plans; and personal news. The Writings and Notes series contains notes and drafts on the Cantos by Sister Bernetta and typescripts of works by Robert Penn Warren, Robert Bly, and James Wright. Personal Papers includes photographs of Pound-related sites and persons in Brunnenberg and Venice.
Quinn, Mary Bernetta, 1915-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn, 1968-1985. For further information, please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Ezra Pound Papers, YCAL MSS 43.
SISTER MARY BERNETTA QUINN, OSF, 1915-2003
Sister Bernetta Quinn was born Viola Roselyn Quinn in Lake Geneva, Wisconsin in September 1915. She entered the Franciscan Congregation of Our Lady of Lourdes in 1934 and made profession of vows three years later. Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn earned a B.A. from the College of St. Teresa in 1942, an M.A. in English from Catholic University in 1944, and a doctorate in English from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1952.
Sister Quinn was a teacher throughout her adult life, first on the elementary and secondary levels and later at many colleges, including Norfolk State College, the University of the Sacred Heart in Tokyo, and Allen University. From 1954 to 1967 she was a member of the English Department faculty at the College of St. Teresa in Winona, Wisconsin.
She also authored several scholarly studies of Modernist poetry, including The Metamorphic Tradition in Modern Poetry (1955); Ezra Pound: An Introduction to the Poetry (1972); and Randall Jarrell (1981), as well as numerous scholarly articles and book reviews.
In 1983 she retired to Assisi Heights in Rochester, Minnesota, and that same year published a small collection of poems, --dancing in stillness. In 1997 she celebrated her diamond jubilee as a Franciscan Sister. Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn died at Assisi Heights on February 24, 2003.
Scope and Contents
The Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn Papers document aspects of Sister Bernetta's literary studies and friendships, particularly those related to the poetry of Ezra Pound. The papers span the dates 1948-1985 and have been organized into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings and Notes; III. Personal Papers; and IV. 1985 Addition.
Series I, Correspondence, is housed in Boxes 1-2 and is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent. With the exception of letters from Ezra Pound himself, the majority of the files contain one or two letters written to answer queries by Sister Bernetta, to thank her for book reviews or articles, or to arrange meetings and talks. This category of correspondents includes the poets Gregory Corso, Robert Creeley, David Gascoyne, Galway Kinnell, Robert Lowell, William Meredith, Seán O'Faoláin, and Louis Zukofsky, and the scholars Marie Boroff, Philip Booth, J. Hillis Miller and Norman Holmes Pearson. The letters of Denise Levertov, for example, are primarily concerned with her request that Sister Bernetta review a volume of Vietnam War protest poetry, while the letter from William T. Stafford explains a confusion between himself and the "poet William Stafford whose mail I occasionally get."
Sister Bernetta's letters from Ezra Pound are located in folders 48-52. Subjects include Pound's humorous comments on Catholicism; her interpretations of his poetry, particularly the Cantos; lists of books Pound recommends to Sister Bernetta; and frequent references to his own political and social views. A letter of June 8, 1952 offers her detailed advice on teaching Dante's Paradiso: "the gt/ heave/ to set up gradations of states of consciousness.... give pupil idea of main architecture." A letter written for "Xmas 1952" contains a long discussion of his theories on usury.
Through her interest in Pound and his poetry, Sister Bernetta met and became friends with several members of Pound's family, including his daughter Mary de Rachewiltz and her mother Olga Rudge. Rudge's letters to her are almost entirely concerned with practical arrangements for her 1967 visit. Mary de Rachewiltz's correspondence with Quinn is more extensive and varied in subject matter. The letters contain personal and family news, particularly news of her children; her work on Pound's archive and her writing of her memoir Discretions; reflections on Pound's life and poetic reputation; and news of various scholarly conferences and meetings devoted to Pound's poetry. The collection also contains several letters from de Rachewiltz's children to Sister Bernetta.
Several other correspondents are closely connected to Sister Bernetta's long-standing interest in the poetry of Ezra Pound. Letters from Marcella Spann and Viola Baxter Jordan decline to contribute personal memories of Pound to an unidentified work. Letters from Guy Davenport, Peter Russell, and James Laughlin discuss news of Pound's failing health, his death in 1972, and the progress of Pound studies in the United States, particularly with reference to the Pound Center at Yale. A letter by Laughlin from 1976 notes that "there should be no more efforts to try to 'correct' Ezra's spellings" and goes on to note "his remarkable ear, and his disregard for the niceties of the eye." A few letters from Guy Davenport comment on C. David Heymann's Ezra Pound: The Last Rower, while others describe Davenport's lectures on Pound's work.
Letters by Robert Bly, located in folders 2-4, contain plans for meetings, comments on current reading and on poetry in general, and discussions of Sister Bernetta's critical work. For example, a letter dated 20 July 1963 details Bly's thoughts on the idea of "symbolism" in modern poetry, and goes on to describe "[Thomas's] desire to fill the poem with such energy that the reason retires exhausted and allows the poem to sink down into the instinctual waters." The letters of Robert Penn Warren contain personal and family news, descriptions of vacation activities, and encouragement and critiques of Sister Bernetta's own writing and academic pursuits.
Series II, Writings and Notes, is housed in boxes 2-4. The first subseries, Writings, contains several articles and poems written by Sister Bernetta Quinn, including "The Metaphoric Spirit" and "A Few Steps Toward Reassessing Stevens." Folder 85 contains a mimeograph sheet titled "The Fourteenth Way of Looking at a Blackbird," which is apparently the record of a group poetry project based on the Stevens poem.
The second and third subseries, Notebooks on The Cantos and Other Notes, consist almost entirely of notes on the content and interpretation of Pound's later cantos as well as bibliographical material relating to Pound. Folder 100 holds notes on Pound's appearance and conversation during Sister Bernetta's 1967 visit with him and Olga Rudge in Rapallo, including Pound's observation that "Rouse's Homer [is] not very musical."
The final subseries, Writings of Others, is alphabetically arranged by author. There are several folders of poems by Robert Penn Warren; folder 109 contains what Warren refers to as the "manuscript" of his 1968 collection, Incarnations: Poems 1966-1968, with the letter that accompanied the gift. James Wright is represented by "The Minneapolis Poem" and "Four Dead Sons (for Sister Bernetta)," as well as by typescripts carbon of other works.
Series III, Personal Papers is organized into the subseries Newspaper Clippings and Photographs, both alphabetically arranged. Folder 125 contains an interview with Sister Bernetta, while folder 124 holds obituary notices for Ezra Pound. Photographs include three folders of color photographs taken in and around Schlöss Brunnenberg in 1974; photographs of Venice taken in 1976; and a portrait of Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century -- Archives; Modernism (Literature); Poets, American -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Bly, Robert, 1926-; Davenport, Guy, 1927-2005; Gordon, Caroline, 1895-1981; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Homes and haunts; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 ( Cantos, Criticism, Textual); Quinn, Mary Bernetta, 1915-; Rachewiltz, Mary de, 1925-; Rudge, Olga, 1895-1996; Stevens, Holly, 1924-1992; Tate, Allen, 1899-1979; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989; Wright, James, 1927-1980
- Correspondence, 1948-1979; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Amanuddin, Syed, 1973 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes typescript poem, "Ezra Pound"
  - Bly, Robert, 1963-75 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Includes printed copy of "Letter to Miguel Otero Silva"
  - Booth, Philip, 1974 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boroff, Marie, 1963 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Borter, Robert J., 1971 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bradley, Scully, 1965 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Page 2 of letter only
  - Carter, Mary, 1973-74 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Close, Virginia, 1966 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cole, Thomas, 1954 May 20
  - Corso, Gregory, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Photocopy
  - Creeley, Robert, 1975 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Davenport, Guy, 1974-78 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - De Loach, Allen, 1970 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    With typescript of article on Cantos
  - Doyle, Charles, 1974 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dyke, Barbara, 1977 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fitzgerald, Joan, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gascoyne, David, 1975 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gay, K. C., 1972 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Giovannini, Giovanni, 1973
  - Gordon, Caroline, 1950-55, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hanson, Polly, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Howley, William, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    With photocopies of letters to Howley from EP
  - Ignatow, David, 1979 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jarrell, Mary, 1976 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jordan, Viola Baxter, 1969 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Keane, Gerard M., 1963-65 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Keene, John S., 1965 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Kenner, Hugh, 1950 May-Jun
  - Kinnell, Galway, 1969, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Klappert, Peter, 1973, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lane, Gary, 1977 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Laughlin, James, 1969-76 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Levertov, Denise, 1972-74 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    With ALS to Levertov from Dennis Rottman and dummy sheet for Winning Hearts and Minds.
  - Logan, John, 1966-74 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lowell, Robert, 1956, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lucas, John, 1959-76 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Lyle, David, 1969 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - McLean, Jean Robert, 1964 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Marcus, Mordecai, 1970 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Meredith, William, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Written on photocopy of "Squire Hazard Walks"
  - Miller, J. Hillis, 1966 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Morse, Samuel French, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Nichols, Bruce, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - [O'Conner], William, 1965 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - O'Faoláin, Seán, 1965 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1973 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - [Peterson, Walter] Scott, 1970 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    With typescript photocopy of "A Doctor's Ultimate Case History"
  - Pound, Ezra, 1949-66, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48-52)
    With TLS from Dorothy Pound, 1950 Apr 18
  - Rachewiltz, Mary de, 1967-76 (Box 1, Folder 53-56)
    With ALS from William Goodreau to Mary de Rachewiltz, 1969 Feb 18
  - Rachewiltz, Patrizia de
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Vroom, Patrizia de Rachewiltz de, Box 2, folder 75
  - Rachewiltz, Siegfried de (Walter), 1968-76, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Raine, Kathleen, n.y. Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Rudge, Olga, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Russell, Peter, 1979 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Saunders, Silvia, 1970 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Shakespeare, A. F., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Sherrard, Elizabeth M., 1962 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert, 1976 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Spann, Marcella, 1970 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Stafford, William T., 1966 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Stevens, Holly, 1964-75 (Box 2, Folder 67-68)
    Includes carbons of letters to others relating to Yale Review
  - Stevens, Wallace, 1948, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Typed transcripts?
  - Sutton, Walter, 1962 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Tate, Allen, 1949-68 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Tate, Isabella Gardner, 1965 Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Thirlwall, John C., 1960-66 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Unterecker, John, 1964-72 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Vroom, Patrizia de Rachewiltz de, 1967, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Wallace, Betty, 1982 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1965-78 (Box 2, Folder 77-81)
  - Weales, Gerard, 1970 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    With typescript poem, "Eighty"
  - Weber, Sally, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Williams, Florence, 1961-63 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Wright, Annie, 1973-75 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Wright, James, 1961-74 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Zukofsky, Louis, 1976 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Unidentified and first name only, 1972-79 (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Writings and Notes, 1961-1981; Series II; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  Series II, Writings and Notes, is organized into subseries and each subseries arranged alphabetically by title, with the exception of the Writings of Others subseries, which is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - WRITINGS
    - "An Afternoon in Wyncote," typescript, corrected, 1967 Mar 31 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - "A Few Steps Toward Reassessing Stevens," typescript, corrected, n.d.
    - "The Fourteenth Way of Looking at a Blackbird," mimeograph of group poetry exercise, 1969 Mar 27 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - "The Metaphoric Spirit," printed, in Margins, 1974 Aug-Sep (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - "Second Look at L'Heureux," newspaper clipping, Boston Sunday Herald, 1967 Apr 2 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - "Two Poems by Sister Bernetta Quinn," printed, in The South Carolina Review, 1975 Nov (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - "Warren and Jarrell: The Remembered Child," typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - NOTEBOOKS ON THE CANTOS
    - "Canto 42ff", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - "Canto 74" (2 notebooks), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - "Canto 81", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - "Canto 96", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - "Canto 98" and "Canto 99" (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - "Cantos 101 and 102, 103" (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - "Cantos 101 and 104"
    - "Canto 105, Canto 106, Canto 109", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - "Canto 110", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - OTHER NOTES
    - "Dartmouth College Notes", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - "Ezra Pound's Brunnenberg library (in part): May 1967" (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - "Notes from my 1967 visit to Rapallo", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - "Pound holdings at SUNY-Buffalo" (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Untitled notebook, [ca. 1967] (Box 3, Folder 107)
      Contains notes on Cantos and other Pound writings; notes on other authors; notes on friends of Pound
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Goodreau, William
      - "When there is no reason to be sad.... for Sister Bernetta", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 108)
        Typescript
    - Russell, Peter
      - "In Honorem Beati Ignati Antiochae," typescript, inscribed to Quinn, 1970 Dec 30 (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - "Gloss: Ayre not Ayer," typescript, inscribed to Quinn, 1979 Mar (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Stevens, Wallace
      - "Two or Three Ideas," photocopy, annotated, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Warren, Robert Penn
      - "Ballad of Mr. Dutcher and the Last Lynching in Gurton," printed copy, 1974 Jan 24 (Box 4, Folder 112)
      - "Bad Year, Bad Man," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
      - Incarnations: Poems 1966-1968, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 4, Folder 114)
        With: TLS from RPW to Quinn, [1968] and bibliography of RPW (incomplete)
      - "Jingle in Tribute to a Great Poem by Marianne Moore," typescript, annotated, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
      - "News Photo," magazine clipping, annotated in two hands, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 116)
      - "Polly on Royal Street before the Raw Face of God," newspaper clipping, 1971 Jan 7 (Box 4, Folder 117)
      - "Rattlesnake Country," Esquire clipping, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
      - "Reading Late at Night, Thermometer Falling," New Yorker clipping, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
      - "Saul at Gilboa," typescript carbon and printed copy from Southern Review (Box 4, Folder 120)
      - "Solipsism and Theology," printed copy (Box 4, Folder 121)
      - "Sunset Walk in Thaw-Time in Vermont," typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Welch, Dennis M.
      - "Robert Lowell's 'Where the Rainbow Ends': A Post-War Act of Faith?," printed copy in The Charter, 1971 Spr (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Wright, James
      - "Four Dead Sons (for Sister Bernetta)," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 124)
        With typescripts carbon of "America for Me," "Sirmione," "The Wheeling Gospel Tabernacle," and "Young Don't Want to be Born"
      - "The Minneapolis Poem," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 125)
      - "New Prose Poems," in American Poetry Review, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 126)
- Personal Papers, 1961-1981; Series III; 0.21; (0.5 box)
  Arrangement
  Series III, Personal Papers, is organized into two alphabetically arranged subseries.
  - NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS
    - Gilbert, Jack, 1964 Nov 16 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Jarrell, Randall, 1961 May 28 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1972-73 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Quinn, Mary Bernetta, 1981, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Warren, Robert Penn, 1974, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Other clippings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
      With tourist map of Rapallo
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Brunnenberg album, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 133-135)
      Color photographs labeled by Quinn; subjects include Schlöss Brunnenberg, interior and exterior; members of the de Rachewiltz family; views of the Alps
    - "Photographs of Venice, 1976" (Box 4, Folder 136)
      Black and white photographs of Pound-related sites in Venice, labeled by Quinn
    - Quinn, Mary Bernetta, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 137)
      With ALS to Donald Gallup, 1973 Apr 23
    - "Rie and family", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 138)
      Color photographs of girl and family members
- 1985 Addition, 1984-1985; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series IV. 1985 Addition is organized into two alphabetically arranged subseries.
  - WRITINGS
    - "Dead in Venice," poem, typescript (photocopy), signed, 1984-85 (Box 5 / Folder 139)
    - "First Visit to San Michele," poem, typescript (photocopy), signed, 1985 May 4 (Box 5 / Folder 140)
    - "Poem for a Troubadour of Greenwich Village (Paul Blackburn)," poem, typescript (photocopy), signed, 1985 May 4 (Box 5 / Folder 141)
    - "Waiting Outside the Classroom at SUNY, Buffalo, for Robert Creeley," poem, typescript (photocopy), signed, 1985 May 4 (Box 5 / Folder 142)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Bibliography, 1985 Apr (Box 5 / Folder 143)
    - Letter to David Schoonover, typescript, signed, 1985 May 4 (Box 5 / Folder 144)